So today we're going
to talk about data.
And where we are is
that you know how
to train a model, given data.
Last time we saw evaluations,
so we know what a good model is.
And for the next two
lectures, this week
we're going to focus on what
data should we train on.
And I want to argue that data
is the most important thing
to get right in language models.
And one justification
for this is
if you look at what
companies actually disclose--
so here is the Llama 3 paper.
They have full transparency
into the architecture--
well of course, because
it's open-weight model--
they even tell you about
their training procedures,
but they don't say
anything about their data.
So they just say, we train
for a variety of data sources
and do some stuff.
And there's good reasons
for this secrecy.
One is that data is your
competitive secret sauce.
Competitive dynamics.
You don't want your competitors
to know what you're doing.
And the second
thing, which we'll
talk a little bit more about,
is copyright liability.
You don't want to get sued if
you tell people you're training
on certain types of data.
So data is a long topic
in machine learning.
And before foundation
models, data work
meant you annotate-- label
data for supervised learning.
Nowadays there's less
manual annotation--
at least in pre-training--
but there's still
a lot of curation and cleaning
work that needs to be done.
And so fundamentally, this
hasn't really changed.
Data has always
been a bottleneck,
and always will be a
bottleneck because it's
in some sense a
long-tail problem,
and that scales
with human effort.
So if you have a lot of people
trying to work on the problem,
well, there's only
so many people
that can work on
architectures and systems.
But data, well, that's--
especially if you're training
a foundation model that's
trying to do all these things,
you can [? paralyze ?]
that effort easily.
So that's why these data teams
and these model developers
are actually quite big.
So data comes in at different
stages of the pipeline.
Today we're focusing
mostly on pre-training.
So pre-training,
you take raw data--
these are documents
from the web.
Then you move into
mid-training where
you train on more
high quality data
to enhance certain capabilities,
and give long context, things
like that.
And then finally
post training, where
you're training on things
like chat transcripts,
or if you're doing
reinforcement learning,
you get some environments
that you're training on.
This becomes more task specific.
In practice the lines
are a bit blurry,
and there could be
more than three stages.
But this is a basic template.
The trend is that
we go from training
on large amounts
of low quality data
to smaller amounts
of high quality data.
So as a result of this process--
you'll see in the literature
when we talk about the base
model, This usually means after
pre-training and mid training,
instruct models or chat
models, or post-training.
But of course, the
lines are becoming
blurry enough that what
is the base model anymore
is really unclear.
And more recently, the largest
models, there's no base model.
There's just Qwen3.5-397B-A17B,
and that's it.
You don't see the
intermediate checkpoints.
So for models that are open
source like OLMo from AI2,
you can see everything
that's happening.
And so, we'll study
some of these models.
So for example, in pre-training,
there's a bunch of sources which
we'll talk about what
these mean, but--
web pages, academic papers,
math pages, proofs, and so on.
There's mid-training--
higher quality web data,
instruction data, bunch of
synthetic data often goes here.
And then finally post-training,
there is a bunch of chat logs.
There are more
math and reasoning,
and coding, you do safety
at this point as well.
So what are all these datasets?
How do you choose them, and
how do you process them?
So that's the main question.
So in the spirit of the class,
we're going to talk about data.
I'm going to go
start from scratch.
So where does data come from?
So one might hear
in the hallway,
oh, language models are
trained on the entire internet.
So first of all, this doesn't
really quite type-check.
Because for that to
be true, it would
have to be an agent that--
like an RL agent that goes
on the internet and does stuff.
But that's not actually
how pre-training works.
Slightly more accurately, it's
trained on the public world
wide web, but this is not
quite accurate for reasons
I'll explain.
OK, so first of all, the web is
actually a bunch of live servers
that just exist in the world,
and you can connect to.
So take any website-- you
can go and download the page.
Or, you can basically send a
request and get back a response.
So you can't actually
train on these live servers
unless you're
training an RL agent.
So typically what you do
is you have a crawler,
or someone builds a crawler,
not necessarily you.
The crawler needs to discover
what web pages are out there,
starting with the seed set, and
it downloads the discovered web
pages as it is crawling.
But still, can't
just run a crawl
and download all the web
pages on the internet,
and there's a few
reasons for this.
One is that a lot of the web
content is actually dynamic.
So especially these days,
a lot of sites are apps.
The URL isn't even as full
[? of ?] specification
of the content, it's just an
app that you interact with,
and you need to often click
buttons or submit forms
to access content.
For example, if you're
on Discord or something,
it's not like you can just crawl
Discord and get all the content
on Discord.
So that's one kind of
thing, and a lot of content
is actually known as in the
deep web, which is not just
doing web page
crawling and following
hyperlinks, which is a very
of traditional model of web
crawling.
The second thing is
that authentication.
So some pages need a login,
an account, and generally
you have to pay.
For example, there's Facebook,
X, LinkedIn, New York Times.
There's actually huge
amounts of content
that are actually locked up
behind these walled gardens.
So these are technically on
the internet or on the web,
but you can't just build a
crawler and go crawl Facebook.
I guess if you're
Facebook, you can crawl--
you don't need to crawl
Facebook, you have the data,
and you can train a model.
Or if you're X AI, you can train
on X. But if you're anyone else,
you can't actually
access this content.
OK, suppose you don't have
the authentication issue.
There's still potential
restrictions here.
So there's something
called robots.txt,
and this is a file
that is usually
placed at the root level of a
directory, such as nytimes.com,
and it basically
tells you what you're
allowed to crawl and whatnot.
So these things are-- a lot
of things are disallowed,
such as OAI-SearchBot, or
PerplexityBot, QuoraBot.
I think basically, ChatGPT-User,
ClaudeBot, and all these things.
OK, so this is not a tech--
this is not a legal
restriction, this
is just like, you're
supposed to be a good citizen
and look at robots.txt.
And if your name
is on that list,
then you should not crawl it.
That's basically the--
not even a contract,
that is the thing
you're supposed to do.
A lot of websites now use
something like Cloudflare
to detect and
block bot activity.
So sometimes you've
gone to a website,
and it gives you a CAPTCHA.
That's because
somehow, some algorithm
has detected that
you might be a bot,
and then it's making
sure you're human.
And if you're actually a
bot, then, well, you can't--
I mean, you could try
to get around this,
but generally this is
an obstacle in your way.
A website might block certain
IP addresses or countries,
and they might have rate limits.
So there's technical
restrictions
on what you can actually
crawl, and then there's
also legal restrictions.
So websites have
terms of service
that say, if you
go to a website,
you have to obey this
contract to use the website.
And the terms of service often
will say, if you're a bot,
go away.
You cannot use this, the content
of the site for AI training,
or whatever it might be.
And also, even if terms of
service don't say anything,
the content of the website
might have a license,
or you might not have
a license to train.
And we'll talk more
about this in a bit.
So there's legal
restrictions on what
you are allowed to train on.
These things are also
evolving over time.
So there's a nice
paper by Shane Longpre
called Consent in
Crisis, and what
they did is they examined
the restrictions--
both the technical
restrictions, robots.txt,
and the legal restrictions,
the term of service,
for various URLs
in common datasets,
which we'll talk about later.
And the conclusion was
that the restrictions
have increased over time.
So here's a graphic that shows--
the top one shows robots.txt.
And if you just
look at this red,
that's the full restrictions.
And up until 2023, everything
was fairly constant.
And then up until mid
2023, all of a sudden
you see the amount of
the fraction of websites
that have full restrictions on
it has grown to almost 50% here.
And for terms, there's a similar
trend where I guess in 2016,
no one really put any
terms on their pages.
And now most pages put some
terms, and most of the terms
say you can't use this for AI.
So even though it was possible
to crawl the internet back in,
let's say 2020, the
internet actually,
at least what you can legally
crawl, is actually much smaller.
So of course, these
are guidelines.
And sometimes,
either intentionally
or not intentionally, you
could violate these things.
So this is-- sometimes you get
into these situations where
there's this guy who--
what was this?
I forget the name of this site--
was complaining about
Anthropic crawling them,
hitting their servers
a million times
in 24 hours, which was not good.
And then Read the Docs
was also getting hammered.
So there was a period where,
which I think probably
has hopefully been corrected
by now, that crawlers
were hammering websites.
And there the-- here,
this is interesting,
is like even before talking
about copyright issues,
there's, I think, problems
with crawling either violating
terms of service, or
robots.txt, or just low up-down,
generating a lot of server
load, which this costs money
for the person hosting it
and also degrades service
for everyone else
trying to use it.
So there are issues
with crawling.
And then, of course,
there's copyright,
which we'll talk about soon.
That's a whole other
complex can of worms.
And then finally, there's these
things called shadow libraries,
which are also part of the web.
So examples are LibGen,
or Anna's Archive.
And these completely disregard
copyright and bypass paywalls.
So someone has collected
a ton of data-- usually
books and articles that
are all copyrighted,
and people have
to pay for these--
and have made them
available for free.
And there have been a lot of
takedown orders, lawsuits,
and these are blocked,
but usually these
are circumvented
because they just make
servers in other countries.
And the people doing this
argue that this is making free
what's freely available,
what should have been freed,
but generally from
a legal perspective,
this is piracy and
copyright infringement.
And we'll come back
to this point later.
So there are a lot of books
and papers on these shadow
libraries.
So the summary so
far, the internet
is a huge and messy
and scary place,
and you can't actually
get all of it.
There are technical
restrictions,
there's legal restrictions
on what data one can access.
So now next time someone says,
I trained on the internet,
you can tell them all
these things you learned.
So now let's go to the second
part of what data can we use,
and this has to
do with copyright.
So suppose you were able to
obey the terms of service,
and you are really
a good citizen,
and you obey the rate limits.
Now, there's still a
question of are you
allowed to train on this data?
And this is a
ongoing question that
has not been fully
resolved, but there
has been a bunch of
developments in the last year.
So the legal context for
thinking about this question
falls into intellectual
property law,
and this is a system
that is trying
to incentivize the creation
of intellectual goods.
So I think it's--
remember, the
spirit of the law is
to not just technically
say no to everything,
but to incentivize the
creation of intellectual goods.
And there's many forms
of intellectual property
that are covered.
There's copyrights, patents,
trademarks and secrets-- sorry,
trademarks, and trade secrets.
The thing that is most relevant
for language model data
is copyright law.
So copyright law has a fairly
long history going back
to the 1700s in England.
And so 1709 was the first time
that governments and courts
started actually
regulating copyright
for this goal of incentivizing
innovation and creation.
And in the US, more recently,
the Copyright Act of 1976
is what I think defines a
lot of modern copyright.
So copyright protection
applies to original works
of authorship fixed in any
tangible medium of expression,
yada, yada, yada.
So a few notes.
So not everything
is copyrightable.
In particular, collections
are not copyrightable.
So for example, if you
have a telephone directory,
unless there is some creativity
in how you arrange things,
this is not really
copyrightable.
And furthermore, copyright
applies to the expression, not
the idea.
So you can't copyright an
idea, like you can't copyright
the quick-sort algorithm.
You can copyright
the implementation
of a quick-sort algorithm, but
not the quicksort algorithm.
So one thing that
happened in 1976
is that the barrier to getting
a copyright was relaxed a lot.
So more things are copyright.
So it used to be that you
had to publish something
to have something copyright.
Now things just
have to be fixed.
And what that means is that
registration of any sort
is not required for
copyright protection.
This is in contrast to patents.
Patents you have to go pay a
lot of money to get a patent,
and you have to file a patent.
But the threshold for
copyright is very low.
For example, you put
something on your website,
it's copyrighted.
That's it.
Now if you want to
sue someone, you
have to go get it registered,
but it only costs $65.
Which is much smaller
than the lawyer fees
that you'll probably
pay, so it's really
still a very low bar.
So one thing to
know about copyright
is that it lasts 75 years, and
then the copyright expires.
And whatever that content gets
released into the public domain,
and this is now--
everyone can use it freely.
So a lot of people who
have lived in the past,
all their great works
are in the public domain,
which is great for everyone.
So the rationale here is that
you're incentivizing innovation.
So when an artist or a
creator creates something,
you want to protect their--
you don't want someone
else to just take it,
so you protect them for a while.
But after 75 years, presumably,
it's not worth protecting,
or they're passed
away, or something.
So it doesn't make sense to
keep things copyright anymore.
So basically, everything on
the internet is copyrighted.
So you're saying, wait a minute.
So that means is everything--
if I train on anything,
that's a copyright violation?
Well, not necessarily.
So everything is
copyrighted, but you
can use copyrighted works.
And the way you do it is A, you
either get a license for it,
or B, you appeal to
the fair use clause.
So a license from
contract law is something
that a licensor
grants to a licensee.
It basically says, don't sue me.
You can use this work in the
ways that the license permits.
So there's a really nice
license called Creative Commons,
which allows something
to act like it
was in the public domain.
It enables free distribution
of copyrighted work.
So examples include Wikipedia,
Open CourseWare, Khan Academy,
all these things.
It was created in 2001
to essentially bridge
public domain and
existing copyright,
because otherwise you
have to wait 75 years.
But what if the creator says, I
actually want people to use it.
They can now have a means,
a legal means of saying,
I put a Creative
Commons license on it.
It's going to act like
it's in the public domain,
and everyone can use it.
So, so far, things
in the public domain
and things that have Creative
Commons licenses are permissive.
You can use it.
But there are many
other times where
you don't have-- it's not
a Creative Commons license,
it's not in the public domain,
you have to get a license.
So if you have money,
you can pay someone
to give you a license.
So there's a bunch of deals
between model developers
and content, I guess,
platforms, that
allow the model developers to
license the data for training
foundation models.
OK, so that's the first thing.
You can get a license--
either Creative Commons,
or you can pay
someone for a license.
Now if you don't
want to pay, you
can appeal to fair use, which
is a more complicated matter.
So this is section 107
of the Copyright Act.
And there are-- basically fair
use says, I can use this anyway,
even if I don't have a license,
and these four factors determine
whether fair use applies.
So the first one is the purpose
or character of the use.
What are you trying
to do with it?
And none of these
are hard rules.
They're just
tendencies which have
to be weighed in court
if it comes to that.
So, for example, if you're
trying to do something
for education, it
is more likely to be
fair use than if you're
trying to sell and make
money off of it.
If you're trying to-- if
you transform something,
then that's going
to be more favored
than if you just literally
host the identical copy.
The nature of the
actual copyrighted work
is also important.
So things that are
more factual are
more likely to be fair
use than fictional works.
Because if you write a
summary of World War--
a page about facts
about World War II,
there's less protection over
my really creative poem.
And then the amount of
portion of the original work.
So using a snippet is
favored over the whole work.
So if you just
take a little bit,
that's not as bad as
taking everything.
So that's fairly
straightforward.
And the final thing is related
to original motivation.
It was like, why are you--
why copyright at all
is to protect and align
the economic incentives.
So the effect that
what the use has
on the market for
the original work.
So if you take an author's work
and you provide an alternative,
and that decreases the amount
that the original author could
monetize their work, that
is seen as potentially bad.
But if you're transforming it in
a way and going to a new market,
or doing something else
with it, then that's
going to be treated
more favorably.
So here are some
examples of fair use.
You can watch a movie and
write a summary of it.
You can re-implement an
idea, like an algorithm--
not copy the code.
And then there was this famous
lawsuit between Authors Guild
and Google.
So if you go to
Google Books, you
can see snippets of various
books which are copyrighted.
So there was a huge
deal about whether this
was deemed fair use, because
you are redistributing
other copyrighted
work, and eventually--
eventually meaning
after 11 years--
this lawsuit was settled
in favor of Google,
which is why this thing exists.
And this has set some
precedent for thinking about
whether language model
training is fair use.
One thing to note is
that copyright is not
about verbatim memorization.
So this might be, I
think, for an ML audience,
this might be a little bit
new because a lot of papers
are focused on
verbatim memorization.
That's one way you can violate
copyright, but not the only one.
So for example, plots and
characters can be copyrightable.
So you can copyright
Harry Potter
the character, not any
particular book, or anything.
But there are some exceptions.
For example, if you're
parodying something--
and so you're creating something
that looks like a derivative,
but as long as you're
making fun of it,
it's actually more
likely to be fair use.
So, yeah.
So a lot of copyright
is about semantics.
It's definitely not
about N-gram overlap,
and also about the economics.
So what is the implication
for language models?
So first off, copying data.
Even if you're not training,
even the mere fact of copying--
which is in the word copyright--
is potentially a
violation already,
even if you don't
do anything with it.
Training a model--
I guess this is not really a--
let's see, how do I take that?
This is not necessarily
a fact, but intuitively
has a transformative flavor.
Because it's certainly not--
it certainly seems
different than just
rehosting another work.
It's doing something
transformative.
And in some sense,
the models are really
trained on this data
as a means to an end.
You are trying to
extract the general idea,
learn about the world
and how it works,
rather than only just
the concrete expression.
And the other thing is that
regardless of copyright,
language models can
definitely affect the market.
So I think this is
also-- remember, that's
the fourth item for fair use.
So by negatively
affecting the market,
you are more likely to
be ruled not fair use.
So fair use is a
little bit slippery.
Suppose you have fair use,
or you have a license.
Remember that there's still
terms of service that allow
or prevent you from actually
just getting a piece of work.
For example, YouTube has all
these videos which are licensed,
but the terms of
service prohibits
just downloading the videos
using a bot, like scraping,
which is another layer.
So there's multiple layers
of restrictions here.
So let me talk a little
bit about where things
are on the legal landscape.
So back in 2023, New York Times
filed suit against OpenAI,
saying you train on our
news articles, and look,
here's evidence.
We were able to actually prompt
ChatGPT to generate a news
article almost verbatim.
I don't think this
is still pending.
There's a case against Anthropic
where the allegation was
you pirated millions of books,
and you trained on these books
to make Claude.
Just last year, this
was a landmark ruling
that said, actually, this
particular instance of training
is fair use.
However, Anthropic,
you're still in trouble
because you pirated all these
books, and that is a no-no.
So notice that this has nothing
to do with training, just
the mere fact of pirating--
I mean, which is
not a new thing--
is illegal.
Anthropic actually,
interestingly,
had bought and
scanned all the books,
which is actually fair use.
The Court said you're
allowed to scan.
You buy a bunch of books,
rip off the bindings,
scan it, and digitize
it for your own use.
That's fair use.
But that doesn't absolve
you of your sin of pirating.
So you can't pirate and then
buy it and say, actually, never
mind what I just did first.
So the outcome is that
Anthropic paid 1.5 billion
to settle the authors.
So this is about $3,000 a book.
So there's also a
lawsuit against Meta.
The allegation was that
you trained on our books--
sorry-- and this was,
as we'll see later,
actually revealed
in the Llama paper.
And the judgment which came
right after Anthropic was, yes,
training is fair use.
And then they also
torrented some books,
so that's still pending.
So that's probably--
if precedent holds,
this is also not going
to be good for Meta.
So the summary so far is
training, so to speak,
has been deemed of
fair use, or at least
has been not deemed
not fair use.
The rulings have
so far been narrow.
It's not to say that any
training on any copyrighted
content is fair use, but
in these cases, it's fine.
Pirating books is
clearly illegal.
I guess we already knew that.
But this is still a very
active and evolving area.
Any questions about
the sources of data?
I think, before we get
into the actual datasets,
I just want to set the
stage with this more
general social context.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
The question is, what do I think
of voice data and ElevenLabs?
I don't know too much about
that, so we can talk offline.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
--because I guess if I own some
asset, it's reasonable for me
to be like [INAUDIBLE].
Am I allowed to-- usually
it's Creative Commons,
but can I update my license
later on to block certain usage?
And so, what is the
role of time playing
in this, like I then train on
the older version with more
a more permissive license
if the creator copied it
to a more restrictive?
Yeah, so the question is,
what happens with time?
If you have one license and then
it gets changed, what happens?
So first, I'm not a lawyer.
But second, so this--
so the first license
I believe you're still
allowed to train on it.
But what happens is
that the license usually
applies to not just, let's
say, a fixed set of documents--
for example, Reddit.
There's constantly new
content being created,
and the license
being changed means
that you wouldn't be able to
train on the later things.
OK, so let's look at
various sources of data.
So let's go back to crawling.
So most model developers
have their own crawler,
because they want to have full
control over what the data is.
Fortunately for the
rest of us, if you
don't want to build
your own crawler,
there's something called Common
Crawl, which has been around
for quite some time since 2007.
And every month they run a
web crawl, gets about three
to five billion web pages.
Each crawl has some overlap
with the previous crawl,
but they try to diversify
and get new pages.
So there's 300 billion
pages so far, which seems--
this was from their website.
It seems a little bit
big, because if you
multiply this number by 20, you
don't quite get 300 billion.
But that's what they say.
So how many URLs are out there?
That's really hard to estimate.
So the Google search index
is at least 100 petabytes,
according to them.
And, each Common Crawl dump
has about 2 billion web pages.
So that's about 372tb.
And this is not
including images,
this is just mostly
focused on the text.
So crawling is conceptually
straightforward,
but all the gory details
are in the implementation.
You start with a bunch of
URLs, and then you iterate.
It's basically graph traversal.
You pop a URL from a
queue, you download it,
and then you look at all
the hyperlinks in that page,
and then you add
them to the queue.
And generally this is done in
parallel over many machines.
And there's many
decisions here--
which pages to download, you
have to respect robots.txt,
don't overload the server.
Sometimes the websites
change, and so you
want a policy that will download
frequently changed pages,
but not spend time downloading
pages that don't change.
So there's some
policy around that.
And I mentioned before,
URLs are dynamic,
so sometimes the same URL
leads to different content
depending on some
state of the browser.
But also, many URLs might
lead to the same content,
so there's a lot
of duplication that
happens if you're not careful.
In particular, mirror sites
explicitly is about duplication.
So Common Crawl releases
their dumps in two formats.
One is a WARC file.
So this is the
raw HTTP response.
So remember, HTTP
protocol is that you
send a get, here's a URL, and
then out comes a HTTP response,
and the WARC file
is that response.
They also do some processing.
They convert to a WET
file, which is necessarily
a loss-y process.
It turns out that this is
not necessarily the best way
to use the web.
The HTML to text,
there's many tools
for this, including
trafilatura and resiliparse,
and the way you convert
actually does matter.
So this is from the
DataComp LLM paper, which
we'll talk a little bit about.
Data is an ablation, where
you look at the web files
that Common Crawl releases
versus these other tools,
and it seems like trafilatura
and resiliparse are better.
So one thing you can do is just
rely on general web crawls.
But often, the web is
not a uniform place.
It's not like there's
a bunch of websites,
and you just get some
random fraction of them,
and that's your dataset.
There are specific pockets of
really interesting, high quality
content, and I'll talk
about three of those--
Wikipedia, GitHub, and arXiv.
So Wikipedia, all
of you know about.
It's been around since
2001, and now there's
67 million articles around
all these different languages.
And Wikipedia is not all
content by any means.
You can't have
original thought in it,
because everything has to
be referenced and cited.
So in some sense you
could argue that Wikipedia
doesn't contain anything
that's not already on the web.
Well actually, that's not
true, because they can also
cite books, which are--
obviously you can't easily get
them, so, Wikipedia is so good.
And also, there's articles
based on notability,
so not everyone can get a
Wikipedia article about them.
So anyone on the internet
can write this content.
This was the radical thing about
wikis, and it's still a miracle,
I think, to me that
this actually works.
It just happens
that any vandalism
gets reverted by administrators,
or bots, I guess, these days.
There's a small number of
Wikipedians-- as any peer
production system,
there's a small set
of people who do
most of the work.
And for example, this
guy has 5 million edits.
And one thing about Wikipedia
is that every few weeks,
they do a periodic dump.
So basically they
take all of Wikipedia
packaged into a nice
TAR file, and then you
can just download that.
So this is important because you
don't need to crawl Wikipedia.
In fact, they don't want
you to crawl Wikipedia.
They just want you to download
this if you're going to crawl,
and this is much
better than crawling.
Just a fun aside,
or good to know,
is that there's this paper
that says you can actually
poison Wikipedia.
So you might think that this
vandalism gets reverted.
So if you do-- attacker
tries to do something fishy,
you'll just get it rolled back.
But what Carlini realized
is that these periodic dumps
happen at a regular cadence.
And so, what you can
do is you can go in
and you can just edit it
right before the dump happens.
And then the dump happens, and
then the edits get rolled back,
but the dump still has
the malicious content.
If you're able to inject
things into web pages,
that means you can cause--
there's works that show that you
can cause the model to, let's
say, ascribe negative sentiment
to any trigger phrase,
like the iPhone.
So one takeaway here is that
if you consider adversaries,
even so-called high
quality contents might
contain bad things in them.
I think this has been
fixed since then.
OK, so GitHub is a
good place for code,
and code is important
not just for
if you want coding capabilities
for your language model,
but if you want
general reasoning.
So GitHub all of you know.
Again, it's a live service
for hosting code repositories.
Been around since 2008, about
the same age as Common Crawl.
It has 420 million repositories,
28 million are public.
Each repository contains--
it's not a file, as you know,
it's a directory with commit
history, issues, pull requests,
and comments.
Code has generally
a lot of duplicates,
and it's just because either
copying code, or forking code.
And GitHub has
deemed it-- you're
allowed to train on
any public repository
with a permissive license.
So MIT or Apache
licenses are fine.
So remember, there's
two types of data
when you talk about GitHub.
There's the
repository data, which
you can just go and download
through the GitHub Git protocol.
And again, you
shouldn't scrape GitHub,
you should just
download the repository.
And then the metadata associated
with each repository-- issues
and pull requests, and so on.
These are made actually via the
GitHub Archive, which gives you
hourly snapshots of this
event stream, which I think
is really interesting data.
It's basically every single
comment, or star, or action
on GitHub that gets recorded.
There's this software
heritage foundation
that is focused on the
repository, not the metadata,
and they aggregate GitHub.
GitHub is not the only
place where code shows up.
There's also smaller entities
like GitLab, Bitbucket,
and so on.
And they aggregate all
that, those repositories
So arXiv, just very briefly--
everyone knows arXiv.
This has been around as
a site that allows people
to share papers since 1991.
Started with physics, and now
has a lot of other areas in it.
Each of the three
million submissions
has the metadata, a PDF,
and optional LaTeX source.
So already you should
be thinking, well,
what does it mean
to train on arXiv?
It's not clear,
because this is, well,
you have to convert
the PDF into text,
or you can use the LaTeX source,
which is a bunch of files.
It's not peer-reviewed, but
there is some approval process,
and authors can choose
to maintain the rights,
or put in the Creative
Commons, which--
so everything is actually
very clearly licensed.
All the metadata is
under permissive license
so you can use that
regardless, and then you can go
and you look at
all the papers that
are Creative Commons license.
You download those,
and you can use them.
And I think most arXiv
papers are Creative Commons.
And then again,
this is available.
You don't crawl arXiv,
you just go down to bulk
download it from some website.
So any questions
about sources of data?
Yeah?
Are there any restrictions
on usage of data,
which is generated by models?
Are there restrictions on data?
Generated by models.
Yeah.
I mean, [? synthetic ?]
[? data ?] models.
Oh, I see.
We'll talk about that
a little bit later.
So the question is, what
about model-generated,
like synthetic data?
Are you allowed to use it?
The short answer
is probably yes.
Yeah?
When using crawlers
like [INAUDIBLE] Crawl
and stuff like that, I guess--
because you mentioned earlier
that there are
websites that have
a lot of pirated books on it.
How do you ensure that
those types of websites
don't show up in your crawl?
Yeah.
So the question
is, there's a lot
of websites with pirated books.
So if you're just
doing a web crawl,
you can't look at
all the websites.
So how do you make sure
that everything is kosher?
And that's part of the
difficulty is, you can't.
And so, there's-- most
likely in Common Crawl,
there are copyrighted books
and content that you are not
supposed to train
on, and you can--
will appeal to fair use.
Remember, everything
is copyright.
Books are not remarkably
different from your website,
for example. both
are copyrighted.
Probably, a book
author has more of a--
if they want to go
into court, they'll
probably be able to protect that
better because it's published
than your website, but still.
And I'll talk a little
bit about later.
If you really, really
want to be careful,
you cam do something
I'll show later.
So what I'm going to
do now is to now talk
about the various
datasets that are actually
used in building models,
starting all the way back
to 2019.
So we've talked about the origin
of data and source of data,
so you have a feeling for just
the general data landscape.
And so, let's start with BERT.
So BERT was from 2018, and
they trained-- back in the day,
they just trained on
Wikipedia and books.
So what is this books?
So there's this website
called Smashwords.
It was created that allow
anyone to just put an ebook up
to publish, and they had about
half a million books in 2024.
So in 2015, there was this paper
who just scraped Smashwords--
sorry, took the books that were
free, and just made a corpus.
This was back in
the innocent days
when no one was paying
attention to any of this.
So this books corpus was
around for many years
in the academic community.
Since then, it has
been taken down
because it violated
the terms of service.
Just because it was free and
you can get it, doesn't mean it
was legally allowed.
So one thing to
note about Bert is
that the sequences were
documents rather than sentences.
All the language
modeling research
before that was
focused on sentences.
So in 2019, GPT-2 came around.
And so what did they do?
So they wanted to get
high quality web content.
And at that time, people
knew about Common Crawl,
but somehow the Common
Crawl data was too messy.
So what they did was came
up with this clever idea
where you can take--
you look at pages that are
outgoing links from Reddit posts
with greater than three karma.
So a good post must
link to good websites.
So you grab those pages,
and you get a 40 gigabytes
of text, 8 million pages.
They never released
this data, but there
was an open
replication of webtext,
which people used quite a bit.
So that's GPT-2.
So as you're going through
this, I guess think about both--
there's many methods of
filtering and collecting data,
and it's interesting to look
at these design choices, and.
So CCNET was developed by,
at that time, Facebook.
So the goal was to create
large high quality data
sets for pre-training.
And they were
especially interested
in low resource languages.
So they didn't want
some very manual process
that only worked for English.
So they did a bunch of things.
They did deduplication,
and language identification
to train a classifier
to detect a language,
and keep only the language
that you're looking for.
And for quality filtering,
the idea that they had was
they wanted to keep documents
that look like Wikipedia.
So Wikipedia at the time was
deemed good, high quality
content, and they used
a language model that
was trained on
Wikipedia, and you
score a probability of a new
document under that language
model to gauge how
Wikipedia-like it was.
So rather than outgoing
links to Reddit,
they use a language
model on Wikipedia.
And they show that because
you can get much more data,
you can actually outperform
just training on Wikipedia.
And this was a tool
that will later
appear in some other papers.
So here is another work.
This is from Google in 2019.
So this is called C4.
So this paper as actually
more famous for the T5 model,
which pushes the idea
that you should just
treat all the NLP tasks in
a world as text-to-text.
But actually, a big
contribution of this paper,
which is a very long
report, was the C4 dataset.
And the observation, which was
very clear at that time, which
is that Common Crawl is mostly
not useful for natural language.
There was this idea that you
have these small datasets,
and they were high
quality, or you had
Common Crawl, which was a mess.
And any attempt to train
on Common Crawl just led
to junk results.
So people were
thinking like, how
do I get a larger but high
quality subset of Common Crawl?
So we saw the Reddit idea, we
saw the Wikipedia-like language
model idea.
C4 used a different
idea, and this
is saying, let's just define a
bunch of rules, which turned out
to be fairly effective.
So basically, they
keep lines that
end in punctuation, that
have more than five words,
remove pages with fewer
than three sentences,
remove pages that
contain any bad words.
Remove things like terms
of use, boilerplate.
Interestingly, remove
the curly brace,
which filters out a lot of
code-- so clearly at that time,
they weren't thinking
about code models--
and they filtered out
anything that was not English.
The end result is that you
have 156 billion tokens,
so 800 gigabytes of text.
So this is much larger than
the GPT-2 dataset, which
was only 40 gigabytes of text.
A bit later there was
some analysis done in C4
which showed--
here's the websites
that were represented.
So you have a
bunch of Wikipedia,
patents was a very common thing.
They also released a
WebText-like document.
They also use this idea
of links in Reddit posts--
from Reddit posts with
greater than three karma,
and filtered to those pages.
So they were able to
get, using this method,
17gb of text using 12
Common Crawl dumps.
Remember, webtext
was 40 gigabytes,
which means that Common Crawl
is maybe incomplete, or doesn't
have everything, because
if it had everything,
you should be able to hit 40.
And they showed
that at that time,
you could use this
data to improve
on a bunch of NLP benchmarks.
So we've seen
using rules, things
that look like Wikipedia,
Reddit links, and now let's
talk about GPT-3.
So GPT-3, the dataset was--
they used Common Crawl, they
did their own processing.
There is this WebText, which was
essentially the GPT-2 dataset,
but expanded.
Notice that there's
some overlap.
Common Crawl does
overlap with this,
but this is, in some sense,
a more targeted distribution.
There is this--
in the paper, it's
described as Books1 and Books2,
which is internet-based books
corpora, so this remains a
mystery exactly what it is,
and Wikipedia.
So the result was
about 500 gigabytes
of text, 400 billion tokens.
And to do the Common
Crawl processing,
they trained a quality
classifier to distinguish things
they deemed to be high
quality from the rest,
and they did some
fuzzy deduplication
because WebText and
Common Crawl had dupes.
So this paper followed the
idea of using a classifier
to do quality classification.
So after GPT-3 came out, this
was, I think, a big event.
And there were a
number of efforts
to try to do things in the open.
So one of the
initial efforts was
The Pile, which is a grassroots
effort from EleutherAI, where
they had a bunch of people
in this Discord just jamming
and figuring out
high quality sources.
And they came up with
this list in the end.
And today, this is still
pretty interesting and diverse.
It has Common Crawl,
it has PubMed.
This has this thing called
Books3, which we'll talk about.
ArXiv, GitHub, which
we talked about.
Wikipedia, IRC, another
BooksCorpus, Philosophy Papers,
and so on.
They included this
Enron Emails dataset.
So Enron went bust in 2002 and
all the emails were released,
and this is one of the few
email datasets we have,
which is a weird distribution,
I think, for email.
But that's what you get.
So Project Gutenberg was--
so let's talk about
books a little bit.
So project Gutenberg
was started in 1971,
and it only includes books that
received copyright clearance.
So mostly books in
the public domain.
There's this packaging
of Gutenberg into PG-19,
which is Gutenberg before 2019.
Which is, I guess most
of them, because for them
to be in public domain,
you have to wait 75 years.
So Books3, which is this
interesting dataset that
appeared in The Pile.
So this is described actually as
200k books from a shadow library
called Bibliotik that concludes
all books from your favorite
authors.
And at that time-- again, 2020,
no one was paying attention.
People used it to train
models, and since then, it
has been taken down.
So you cannot use, or should
not use Books3 anymore.
We'll come back to Books3 again.
So Stack Exchange you've
probably used quite a bit,
although I guess these days
maybe less so because of AI.
There's a bunch of
user-contributed questions
and answers, started in 2008.
And one thing that is
interesting about this dataset
is that it's a Q&A
format, and this is quite
close to a real application.
So normally, you think about
pre-training data as here's
Wikipedia articles,
just like raw text.
But some parts of the
web are actually--
look supervised, like
what you would want
to ask your language model.
Which I think, maybe,
helps the model
learn certain types of
question answering behaviors.
So not everything is
super magically emergent.
It's like, well, this type of
data does exist on the web.
So there's also-- this
data has metadata,
which is like the
number of votes
which are useful for filtering.
And again, this data is
released in data dumps
that allows you to just
download without crawling it.
So now we're in 2021.
There was another
paper from DeepMind.
They trained a
model called Gopher,
which was never
released, and actually
was subsumed by Chinchilla.
But the description
of the data, I think,
is actually really good.
You should read this
paper, because I
think it's very
thorough in the way
that they describe
the data processing.
Well, except for the parts
where they don't tell you
what's in the data.
So they created
this massive web,
and they had C4, which
remember, was the dataset
that we looked at
before from Google.
They train on books, news,
GitHub, and Wikipedia.
They don't say anything
about how they got that.
So for the MassiveWeb,
they kept English, deduped,
and their quality filtering
was also based on manual rules.
And part of the reason
for this is that they
had more control over that.
So I think, as
you can see, there
is this division between
people who wanted to use rules,
and people who wanted
to use classifiers.
So they got, as
the name suggests,
a massive amount of
text, but their model
was only trained on a very
small fraction of this dataset.
So in 2022 Llama 1 came out,
and the dataset here-- this
was actually a very nice paper
in that it detailed their data
processing.
So this is probably one
of the last non-open,
fully open models that
actually talk about their data
processing.
So they have Common Crawl
processed with CCNET,
which you know about.
The classification, though,
was whether the page
was a reference of Wikipedia,
not whether it is actually
a Wikipedia article.
So the idea is that well,
maybe Wikipedia articles
are too stylized.
And we know that Wikipedia
articles references
a bunch of other articles
which are presumably good,
so let's call those
the good websites.
They had C4, they did
a bunch of processing
on GitHub to keep permissive
licenses, Wikipedia.
They trained on Books3
and project Gutenberg.
So Books3 really got
them in a lot of trouble
because they're just
announcing to the world that
hey, I trained on this dataset.
And if you look
back, oh, this came
from-- where did it come from?
It came from The Pile.
Oh, it came from
a shadow library.
So that's why people don't
want to talk about their data
anymore.
So they looked at
arXiv, and actually used
the LaTeX to do the
processing, Stack Exchange,
and they got 1.2
trillion tokens.
They didn't actually
release this dataset,
but they had enough of a
description in their processing
that this was reproduced
by Together's RedPajama V1
dataset, which was then
used in other sources.
So as you can see
here, RedPajama V1
initially also contained Books3,
which has now been stripped out.
So various decisions made early
on about copyright actually
influence-- have a
fairly big watershed.
So let's talk about RefinedWeb.
So this is a paper that tried
to make a point that web data is
all you need.
So the web, in some
sense, is everything.
And then we talked about
all these specialized
sources, like there's GitHub
and arXiv, and Stack Exchange.
And they said,
well, what happens
if we just stick with the web?
So they did a good job of doing
the transformation from HTML
to text.
They filtered using the Gopher
rules, which is basically keep
things that look like English.
They explicitly,
at that time, still
said avoid ML-based
filtering to avoid biases.
I don't want to find an overly
narrow subset of the web.
They did some deduplication, and
they had five trillion tokens.
They released about
600 billion of them.
So FineWeb from Hugging Face
was a replication of RefinedWeb,
but improved it.
So they took all the Common
Crawl dumps at that time,
did some filtering--
again, using manual rules
to not inject biases--
deduped, did PII removal,
and got 15 trillion tokens.
So you can see that the
size of these datasets
is growing quite a bit.
So then there is this
Dolma dataset from AI2,
and this is a dataset that
includes their own processing
of Common Crawl, The Stack,
which we'll talk about,
before C4, which you know about,
and a bunch of other things.
And the Reddit dataset was from
this project called PushShift.
And at that time, you
could still get this data,
and you can train on it
before things got locked down.
AI2 has their own crawl
of academic papers called
Semantic Scholar, so they
derived a dataset based on that.
So let's look at their
Common Crawl processing.
So they use language
identification.
So this was model-based,
but quality filtering still
avoid model-based filtering.
And then they removed toxicity
using rules and a classifier.
And they got three trillion
tokens out of that.
So DCLM, I think,
was maybe a point
where this idea of
model-based quality filtering
started to really
become the norm here.
So DataComp, the
initial motivation
was to define some
sort of pipeline
so that people can try different
data methods in a standard way,
and show results.
But I think the main
way that I think
people use this is just using
their dataset that they released
to train models and
do other things.
So they processed Common
Crawl to produce DCLM-pool.
So this is completely
unfiltered.
And if you look at this
dataset, this is massive.
240 trillion tokens.
This is probably more
than the number of tokens
that anyone really trains on.
But a lot of this is
fairly low quality,
so then they had a pipeline
where all that gets filtered.
If you only keep
English, you have
some of rules to
really narrow it down.
You do dedupe, and then you
do this model-based filtering,
and you end up with
something that's 1.4%.
And this is the data set
that we'll see actually works
pretty well.
So the model-based filtering--
and this was strangely good.
So to train a classifier,
they took OpenHermes,
which is essentially
instruction data that
was generated by
GPT-4, and ELI5,
which is a subreddit with
various questions and answers.
So this is-- let's see.
These are the type of
questions that are in ELI5.
So anyway, you get the idea.
So it's kind of weird,
but somehow this works.
So the negative examples are
anything from RefinedWeb, which
is, remember, it's just a
very loosely filtered version
of the web.
It's basically the web, and
it got 3.8 trillion tokens.
They train a fastText
classifier-- think about it just
as a linear classifier.
And then they show that this
magical classifier, quality
classifier, outperforms a bunch
of other things that they tried.
So, DCLM.
This became, for a while, at
least in the open community,
a bit of a gold standard
for quality filtering.
Let's move on to Nemotron.
So Nemotron-- this
is from NVIDIA--
they said that well, DCLM
filters too aggressively.
It's removing most of the data.
And remember, they only got--
how many-- 3.8 trillion tokens.
So we need more tokens.
So what do we do?
We are going to do something
more, I guess, elaborate.
We're going to
prompt our existing
model to score FineWeb documents
based on educational value.
So we're going to prompt
a language model and say,
is this educational or not?
Go add a bunch of labels,
train a fastText model.
So that's one classifier.
Another classifier is just
using the DCLM classifier.
So we're going to use
those classifiers.
We're also going to
use synthetic data.
So this is probably one of the--
I don't know if-- it's
probably not the first,
but, one of the main
datasets that really
lean into synthetic
data for pre-training.
So they had, for
low quality data,
as deemed by these
classifiers, you
use a language model to
rephrase it to make it more--
look like Wikipedia.
For high quality data,
we use a language model
to generate various tasks.
For example, given
a Wikipedia article,
I can generate
question answers, or I
can generate like, please
summarize this document,
extract key information
from it, and so on.
So they resulted in a dataset
that was 6 trillion tokens.
So this is substantially
larger than DCLM.
And just for reference,
this is still kind of
small by some consideration.
So Llama 3 was trained
on 15 trillion tokens,
Qwen3 was trained
on 36 trillion.
Although there is this--
it's not clear how big
these unique tokens are,
because when you look at
[INAUDIBLE] counts in language
modeling papers, some
of it is repeated.
Like if you do
two epochs, that's
twice the number of tokens,
so you have to be careful
when you look at those numbers.
And they show that
the dataset is better.
Their high quality subset
beats the previous datasets
So up until now, we've seen
a bunch of different methods
for filtering.
I think all of these look
very similar at some level.
You take a web crawl,
you either decide
I'm going to use
rules to filter,
or I'm going to use a model.
If I'm going to
use a model, then I
have to decide what
looks like good data,
and then try to
train a classifier,
and classify all my
documents, and select.
And there seems
to be a trade-off
between you can take a
lot of Common Crawl--
you can get 240 trillion
tokens if you want,
but that's probably going
to be really low quality.
Or you can get one
trillion tokens,
and there's some
sweet spot in-between.
Let me talk about
two final things.
So code, and going back to
this question of licensing.
So The Stack is a
very nice project
that was trying to make a really
good coding data set, since it
was clear by 2022
that coding was
going to be really important.
So what they did in
the initial version
is that they clone 137 repos.
They kept the ones that
were permissively licensed,
remove near-duplicates, and
resulted in one-- sorry,
three terabytes of code.
And then in 2024,
they had an update.
And here they took
more the metadata,
like the issues, comments,
and PRs from GitHub,
the repositories from
the Software Heritage,
which we talked about.
They also scraped documentation
from various websites
by crawling them.
They did a bunch of processing.
So in GitHub repos, you have
binary files which you probably
don't want to train on.
They have malware,
you get rid of that.
A lot of GitHub, especially
these PRs, are bots,
so you have to filter that.
Dedupe, do PII redaction.
There's a lot pull
requests and stuff,
and they basically subsample
to keep it representative
and the dataset manageable.
They also did this thing,
which was I thought was nice,
which is that there's many
programming languages out there.
There's a lot of
Python, a lot of C,
but low resource languages like
Nim-- which I hadn't even heard
of-- they're not that common.
So what they do is
they compile this code
into a low-level
intermediate language,
LLVM, which everything, like C
Compiler, can compile into this,
and they have juxtaposed
the low resource
language and the
intermediate representation.
So then the language
model can actually
learn the mapping between the
shared low level representation,
which has a lot of data on,
and the thing that it does
has less data on.
And just for fun, you add
in all the other good stuff
that you can.
So Stack V2 is
mostly code, and then
plus other things that were used
to train their coding models.
And one thing
about pull requests
is that pull requests and
all the metadata is not,
by its nature, a
linearized sequence.
So there has to be some
steps taken to linearize it.
So one important thing
you have to decide
is how much context to provide.
So for example, an
event might just be,
I change one line of code.
And that could just be
one line, but presumably
to learn that, you want to
provide some context, maybe
a few lines around it, or maybe
the entire file surrounding
that diff.
And these are some
design decisions
that you have to make
for linearization.
And so at the end of the day,
the tokens that they train on
look something like
this, where it's
this XML-like structured
data, where you have the PR,
and then you have
a bunch of diffs.
And then for comments, you
have basically the events
of a comment was posted, what
the review state of that PR was
and so on and so forth.
So it's not just
learning how to generate
code, but also the software
development process around code.
So finally, I'll talk
about the common pile.
So recall that almost all
the data on the internet
is copyrighted.
Some of it is permissively
licensed, some of it
is even in the public domain.
And while you can appeal
to fair use and say,
I'm going to train on it anyway,
this is not quite settled.
So if you're very,
very risk-averse,
then you say, well, if I
don't know whether it is OK,
that's a no.
If you take that attitude, then
that's what common pile did.
So can you train a good model
with only permissively licensed
data?
Or rather, how far can you get?
So this was a project that
went and scoured the internet
for all the different
types of data
that they could possibly find
that was worth training on,
that was permissively licensed.
It includes Stack V2 in code.
It turns out that a lot
of government proceedings
are actually
permissively licensed,
wikis, some things on the web--
some new sites are actually
permissively licensed,
academic papers, online forums,
things that are in the public
domain, educational resources,
and so on.
So in the end, there
were 8 terabytes
of data, which is
actually pretty
good for permissively
licensed data.
Doing this project is
actually much harder
than maybe it sounds
at first glance.
It's not just as simple
oh, you look at the license
and it's like, oh yep,
Apache, or CC, good.
There's some subtleties,
versus license laundering.
So people are sloppy
with licenses.
So people might take
some copyright work
and just slap a CC BY on it.
Anyone can write
this on the internet,
and it's hard to tell
whether this is real or not.
There's also this common
practice where, for example,
Dolma is permissively licensed.
Remember, Dolma is
the AI2 collection.
But collection licenses don't
extend to the individual works.
So the collection is--
I mean, first of all,
there's a question
of whether collections--
I think collections
can be copyrighted,
but I guess you can put
a license on anything.
But the individual works
are not necessarily good.
So you can't just look at
data sets on Hugging Face,
and you-- many data sets
on Hugging Face you see,
they have a permissive license.
But if you dig
deeper, it's actually
not permissively licensed
at the individual level.
And they also made a
decision to forego training
on any synthetic data, because
training language models
on unlicensed data is unclear.
So probably it's fine
because technically, these
are open weight models
with MIT license.
You can do whatever.
You can use them
however you want,
but these language models
were presumably also trained
on unlicensed data.
So it's a little bit
of data laundering
if you are really honest here.
So with this data,
they compare it
with a bunch of other models
like the first Llama, MPT,
and Qwen.
And on a bunch of benchmarks,
they show that this is not bad.
I would say it's not as good
as the Qwen models for sure,
but it's certainly
outperforming the very old--
this is from 2023, I guess.
So quite old models.
So I would say,
the conclusion here
is that you can do
reasonably, but I
think it's still
pretty tough to compete
without doing more tokens.
But I don't think this
is the final word on it,
and I think you can probably
eke more out of publicly
permissive licenses if you try.
OK, so to summarize
this lecture here.
So maybe hopefully now I've
given you some appreciation
that data is a very rich topic.
It's not that data just
falls from the sky,
or you just go on Hugging Face
and you download a dataset.
Data has to come from somewhere.
And there's also a technical
but also social context
in which data comes,
because at the top,
the internet is a
bunch of live services.
Someone has to do the work
of producing raw data,
whether it be the website
that gives you dumps,
or someone has to build
a crawler, or something.
And then, someone has to make
the decision of how to process
it into usable form--
filtering, transformation,
deduplication, all these things
have an impact on the quality
of your final language model.
And notice that
filtering is probably one
of the most important things.
How do you go from
200 trillion tokens
to less than three
trillion tokens?
I think that obviously is a
huge reduction, which I think
merits a lot of attention.
Data is, in some sense,
a key ingredient that
differentiates language models.
A lot of language models
are roughly the same kind
of transformer architecture,
but data is depending
on how you process it.
It can make a pretty
big difference.
There's plenty of legal
and ethical issues
around data, more than I
can get into this lecture.
And also, this
process is very messy.
Unlike some of the other parts
of this class where things
are maybe more based
on first principles,
data processing is, right
now at least, a lot just
based on vibes you set up.
You define this classifier,
you define this rule,
you set some threshold.
So there are many
opportunities to improve.
So as you do your
assignment four,
maybe think about whether
there's better ways to do this,
and this could be maybe
a research direction.
OK, so that's it for today.
So next time I'll continue
talking about data.
I'll talk a bit about
post-training data,
and a bit more about filtering.